If somebody asked you what the deadliest
mountain in the world is, your first
thought would probably wander to ones
that are obviously very dangerous like
Mount Everest or maybe even K2. If
you're familiar with the world's second
tallest mountain's brutal reputation. If
you were limited to answering the
deadliest mountain in the United States,
you might think of examples like Denali
in Alaska, Mount Reneer in Washington,
or Mount Hood in Oregon. All of these
mountains indeed have infamous
reputations, and they all look extremely
intimidating as well. That's probably at
least partially why you've actually
heard about them. But what if I told you
that instead the deadliest mountain in
America and indeed the deadliest
mountain in the entire world isn't
actually any of these, but is rather a
much much smaller and unassuming looking
mountain in New Hampshire that you've
maybe never even heard about if you're
not from around here that's called Mount
Washington. With a total elevation of
6,288
ft above sea level, Mount Washington is
the tallest summit that can be found
anywhere in New England and more broadly
anywhere in the entire northeast region
of the United States. Nonetheless, when
compared to the elevations of mountains
elsewhere across the western US, Mount
Washington appears as basically a dwarf
mountain. Despite being the tallest
mountain in the Northeast, it is only
the 550th tallest mountain nationwide
with literally hundreds of mountains
taller that it dotted all across states
west of the Mississippi across the
Rockies, the Sierra Nevada, and the
Cascades. In fact, it's less than half
the height of dozens of mountains found
across Colorado and Alaska. And yet, it
is claimed more people's lives than
nearly all of them anyway. Since 1948,
more than 32 people have died on Mount
Washington due to a combination of
falls, avalanches, and hypothermia. More
than every other mountain in the United
States other than Denali, Mount Reneer,
and Mount Hood. Mount Washington is tied
for the fourth highest number of deaths
on any mountain in the country, tied
with Grand Teton in Wyoming. And of
course, the principal attribute of Mount
Washington that sets it apart from all
these other deadly mountains is its
dramatically shorter height. Mount
Washington is less than a third the
height of Denali and is roughly half the
height of Mount Reneer, Mount Hood, and
Grand Teton. Despite having the same
number of fatalities since 1948 as the
latter, since modern recordkeeping began
a century before that in 1848, more than
160 people are known to have lost their
lives on Mount Washington. Adjusted for
the number of deaths per foot of
vertical climb, Mount Washington becomes
not only the deadliest mountain in
America, but the deadliest mountain
anywhere in the world. A fact that
becomes all the more strange when you
realize that you can simply drive a car
or take a train all the way up to the
summit. Unlike any of these other super
deadly mountains that are dramatically
taller than it, where the only way yep
is basically to climb. This is in a
sense precisely what makes Mount
Washington so deadly. the fact that it
simply doesn't appear to be deadly like
all of the other mountains do on the
list of deadliest mountains. Denali is
in an extremely remote location in rural
Alaska that isn't connected to any
roads. You basically have to charter a
plane just to fly you to Denali's base
camp. And climbing up from there and
back again often takes weeks to
accomplish through massive glaciers and
creass fields that are apparent from
miles away before you even get there.
Mount Reneer is similarly covered in
glaciers full of cavernous creasses that
are large enough to swallow up entire
houses all that you can see from far
away. While hiking up more than 10,000
vertical feet through all of that in
order to reach the summit serves as too
much of a deterrent for most. The kind
of people who decide to climb these
kinds of mountains are usually well
aware of how dangerous they are and have
spent a serious amount of time and
effort preparing to tackle them. Mount
Washington, on the other hand, doesn't
really look all that different from just
about any other mountain within its
range in New Hampshire, the White
Mountains. There aren't any glaciers
that are present to frighten people
away. [music] And unlike many of the
other deadliest mountains, it's hardly
in a remote location that's difficult to
get to. [music] It's only about a 3 and
1/2 hour drive from the big city of
Boston to reach the parking lot at the
base of the mountain. And from there, it
can only take all of about two hours for
an unprepared hiker to get in way over
their heads and capabilities. The summit
of Mount Washington is actually the
sixth most visited mountain summit in
the world. Largely because of how
accessible it is from major metropolitan
areas like Boston, the fact that you can
usually just drive or take a train all
the way up to the summit, and its status
as the highest peak in New England in
the Northeast. But all of the other
mountain summits in the topmost visited
are either much shorter and therefore
safer or they're much higher and
therefore people know to prepare better.
Mount Washington is basically at this
weird middle sort of height where
underprepared climbers or even drivers
expecting something easier might get
caught off guard, especially when luck
doesn't favor them. It's not really
Mount Washington's height that makes it
so incredibly deadly, though. It's the
fact that the mountain arguably is the
site of the worst weather that can be
found anywhere on planet Earth. Despite
its rather unassuming looking
appearance, let's start with wind and
explain why Mount Washington is actually
the single windiest location anywhere in
the world. On an afternoon day in April
of 1934, researchers at the summit of
Mount Washington at Mount Washington
Observatory measured a wind speed that
should have been impossible, an
astonishing 231 mph. To put that into
perspective, in order to become a
category 5 hurricane, wind speeds only
need to reach 157 mph. 231 mph is enough
to obliterate any house made out of wood
and will even cause serious structural
issues to well-built houses. For
decades, that measurement on the top of
Mount Washington was the fastest wind
speed ever measured anywhere on the
Earth's surface until it was surpassed
in 1996 by a monster tropical cyclone
that clocked in at a speed of 254 mph
off the western coast of Australia. It
is still the fastest wind speed ever
measured on the Earth's surface outside
of the context of a tropical cyclone or
a tornado. Hurricane force winds or wind
speeds greater than 75 mph are generally
observed on the summit of Mount
Washington for an average of 110 days a
year or for nearly one out of every 3
days. And during the winter season, the
wind speeds will be at or above
hurricane force about every other day on
average. the most consistently
dangerously fast winds that are
experienced anywhere in the world. These
wicked fast winds that blow over Mount
Washington are of course a frequent and
significant hazard and they happen for
an interesting culmination of reasons.
Mount Washington, while not exactly a
tall mountain compared to those out
west, is still a giant in the east. Its
summit is the highest geographic point
for nearly a thousand miles away in
every direction. It happens to exist at
almost exactly the midpoint between the
North Pole and the equator. And it sits
precisely at the intersection of three
major weather systems from the Atlantic
to its south, from the Arctic to its
north and its west, and from the Gulf of
Mexico to its far southwest. These three
clashing weather systems bring warm,
humid tropical air from the southwest,
moist maritime air from the Atlantic,
and cool, drier continental air from the
north. All precisely to the summit of
Mount Washington, where they clash and
generate powerful low pressure systems
and strong pressure gradients, which
drives the freak storms and extreme
winds up there. Wind is usually slowed
down by friction from the ground. But
since Mount Washington is by far the
highest point anywhere around for
thousands of miles in most directions,
the higher winds that strike it haven't
ever been slowed down by this usual
process. The overall presidential range
the Mount Washington crowns in the north
forms a Vshape that points directly
where the cold winds blowing across
southern Canada come from. As the higher
winds that haven't been slowed down for
thousands of miles reach the
presidential range, they're suddenly
forced upward and accelerate in speed
through a process known as the Venturi
effect. Similar to how a river's
velocity increases as it passes over a
rapid. This combined with a clashing of
cool, dry air with warm, moist air is
what can create some of the most
freakish weather on the planet up here
and going well beyond just the insane
wind speeds. As you'd expect for a
mountain at its elevation and its
latitude, it gets pretty cold up on the
summit of Mount Washington. The summit's
all-time low recorded temperature was
-50° F back in January of 1885. A high
temperature of 0° F still occurs about
13 days a year. While low temperatures
at or below 0° F usually happens every
single day between the middle of
November and the start of April. Between
December and March across the winter
season, the temperature on the summit
will only get above freezing for an
average of just 15 days. Across the
whole year, the average ambient
temperature on the summit is just 27° F.
Now, a lot of that might not sound too
bad to be honest, but you have to
remember that none of those ambient
temperatures take into account the crazy
fast wind speeds and the absolutely bone
shattering windchill effect they have.
To give you just an idea of how nuts
this can get, consider the horror that
the mountain summit experienced on the
16th of January in 2004. That day, the
ambient temperature on Mount Washington
summit was -46.3°
F or -42 C. Already very cold, but it
was also sustaining wind speeds of just
over 87 mph, too. As a result, the wind
chill value on the summit that day was a
brutal -12.6°
F or74.7°
C. Enough to cause frostbite to exposed
human tissue in under 5 minutes in
lethal in as little as 30 minutes
without proper Arctic survival gear. And
then somehow even that brutal record was
beaten pretty recently over the night of
the 3rd to 4th of February 2023 when an
ambient temperature of -47° F and faster
wind speeds of more than 100 mph
produced a new record low US windchill
temperature on the mountain summit of
-18°
F. Simply put, that is nearly as cold as
the coldest surface air temperature ever
recorded in history, which was measured
at -128.6°
Fahrenheit in 1983 at the Vtop station
deep within the interior of Antarctica.
The summit of Mount Washington can
therefore literally get as cold as the
depths of Antarctica can during the
winter. And it is rather surprisingly
the site of the coldest temperature ever
measured anywhere in the United States,
even beating out anywhere in Alaska.
During that event in 2004, when the wind
chill effect plunged the temperature
down to as low as -102.6°
F, the wind chill never once rose to be
warmer than -50° F for more than 71
hours or for nearly three straight days.
Even throughout the summer months,
temperatures can unexpectedly plunge in
winterlike conditions can exist at the
summit, which is the next big dangerous
problem on the mountain. Dune Mount
Washington's location along clashing
weather patterns, its relative proximity
to the Great Lakes that brings lake
effect snow along with the Canadian
winds, and its relatively high elevation
compared with its surroundings, Mount
Washington gets a ton of snow, which is
extremely unusual for its modest
elevation. Mount Washington Summit will
see an average of almost 97 in of
precipitation per year. The vast
majority of which falls on it as snow,
which is surprisingly even more
precipitation than the summit of Mount
Reneer in Washington receives despite it
being about twice as tall. Mount
Washington receives by far the most snow
of any mountain of its height or lower
anywhere in the United States. For
basically the same reasons why it's so
windy up there, too. Huge volumes of
snow will get picked up all along the
lower presidential mountains and then
gets blown up across Mount Washington
over to its eastern side where the snow
packs and fills up deep ravines there
like Tuckerman that can sometimes reach
up to 50 ft deep during the winter. In
the winter and the spring, this thickly
packed snow, especially in Tuckerman
Ravine, can morph into an almost
concrete like layer that can easily
fracture and generate avalanches, which
is a major hazard for hikers and
backcountry skiers all throughout the
winter and spring seasons as well. Many
of whom might not expect such a
potentially high avalanche risk for such
a relatively small mountain. As recently
as 2024, backcountry skiers have lost
their lives because of this here in the
Tuckerman Ravine by falling hundreds of
feet. And as recently as 2012, a man
slipped and slid down the side of
Tuckerman Ravine in April [music] and
then fell into a hidden creass. And his
body wasn't able to be recovered for 7
weeks. Others have gone missing on the
mountain for years until the remains
were discovered. sometimes [music] being
buried beneath dozens of feet of snow
during particularly catastrophic
avalanche events, while others simply
wander off too far away from the road or
the railroad that takes you up safely to
the summit and get trapped alone up
there when the weather suddenly turns
for the worse. Near the summit, it can
literally go from relatively nice to
blizzard-like and life-threatening
within minutes. While temperatures can
plunge by upwards of 20° just as
quickly, and they're very difficult to
predict. And if all of those hazards
weren't enough, there's also the added
concern of what is often very, very
limited visibility up on the summit of
Mount Washington as well. With all the
wind, storms, and precipitation that
falls on Mount Washington, cloud cover
up there is nearly constant all
throughout most of the year. In fact,
only about 50 days out of the entire
year on average are clear on the summit
between sunrise to sunset. Visibility
conditions near the sun can and do
rapidly deteriorate within minutes
sometimes, just like with the
temperature, including complete white
outs and literally zero visibility where
you can't even see more than a foot or
two ahead of you. These poor visibility
conditions, when they happen suddenly
and unexpectedly, can be particularly
dangerous for hikers or backcountry
skiers, when they're nearby [music]
massive cliffs and drop offs like the
Tugerman Ravine, which features plunges
of up to 600 ft. In some locations, if
you get blinded during a total white out
up there and become disoriented on your
location, it's not inconceivable to see
how you might just take one wrong step
into an abyss like that.
Now, there's a lot of places in the
world that have worse conditions in a
single category than Mount Washington
does, but very few of them combine all
of these factors together in such an
overwhelmingly negative way. The Vosto
Research Station in the middle of
nowhere Antarctica might get colder than
Mount Washington does, but it has
nowhere near the same level of wind
speeds with a yearly average of just 11
mph. And it also receives virtually zero
precipitation or snowfall either.
Hurricane and tornado-prone areas may
experience similar freak wind speeds,
but they're nowhere near as frequent,
and they're never in areas that get
anywhere near as cold. Denali and Alaska
might have a much higher summit and
lower oxygen levels in a more remote
location with similar visibility issues,
but Denali gets virtually zero
precipitation and doesn't get anywhere
near as windy. And again, for the most
part, Mount Washington doesn't exactly
appear to be dangerous for most of the
climb up it until you get beyond the
mountains tree line. The wicked fast
winds that whip across Mount Washington
contribute to a very unusually short
tree line at only about 4,400 ft up in
elevation. With the climate any further
up, simply too hostile to support any
plant life more than just a few inches
in height. The climate also radically
changes very quickly as you climb up
Mount Washington. In [music] the
mountains parking lot, you're
experiencing a humid continental climate
that's typical for New England. But as
you move up it, you quickly transition
through a subarctic climate until you
reach the end of the tree line where it
immediately transitions into a tundra
climate not too dissimilar from Labrador
or Greenland the rest of the way up to
the summit. This can often catch hikers
offg guard on Mount Washington who don't
expect to be going from a calm walk
through the woods at the mount's lower
elevations to a potentially lethal walk
through the Labrador or Greenland tundra
further up beyond the tree line. The
treeless upper reaches of the mountain
towards the summit are fully exposed
with zero cover to hide behind or take
shelter in when weather conditions
rapidly turn for the worse with the
infamous super fast winds, white outs,
and plunging temperatures. A total of 65
acres of Mount Washington's Peak is
classified as tundra terrain, which is
again, perhaps unexpectedly, the most
tundra present on any mountain east of
the Rockies. The potentially extreme
life-threatening danger of being exposed
to the brutal elements beyond the tree
line on your climb up towards the summit
is not apparent to most people who climb
the mountain. And it's only when you're
far removed from both the treeine and
the summit about halfway up that you
might realize just how deep into this
quiet danger zone you've gotten yourself
into. While the elevation of the tree
line ends at 4,400 ft above sea level,
it only takes about 3 mi worth of hiking
from the parking lot in order to reach
it, which is notably significantly less
hiking than it even takes to reach the
base camp on Mount Reneer in Washington.
In other words, you can reach the most
dangerous zone on Mount Washington
before you even reach the base camp on
Mount Reneer, which is a recipe for
disaster for hikers who aren't coming as
well prepared as they usually do for
Reneer. Near where the tree line ends on
Mount Washington, the US Forest Service
has put up ominous signs on trails like
this one, warning that the area ahead
beyond the trees contains the worst
weather in America and that hikers have
lost their lives to the elements out
there exposed even during the summer.
Then there's also the fact that Mount
Washington is actually a lot more of a
climb than many people might initially
expect as well. While it is only the
550th tallest mountain in the United
States by elevation above sea level,
Mount Washington's prominence is
substantially more impressive than that.
Prominence is a measurement of how much
a mountain stands out relative to its
surrounding terrain and is basically the
vertical distance between a mountain
summit and the lowest point you have to
descend to before climbing up a higher
peak. In Mount Washington's case, you
have to descend from its summit all the
way down to 140 ft in elevation at the
Champlain Canal before journeying toward
the higher peak at the Potato Knob all
the way down in North Carolina. This
means the nearly all of Mount Washington
sea level elevation is pure prominence
since it rises from a very low
elevation. 6,148
ft of its height is prominence to be
precise. And this gives Mount Washington
astoundingly the 24th highest prominence
of any mountain in the contiguous 48 US
states beyond Alaska and Hawaii with a
greater prominence than even some of the
14,000footers out west in Colorado like
the well-known Pikees Peak. This means
that despite its overall elevation being
only a fraction of most mountains out
west, actually hiking up Mount
Washington includes a similar vertical
height to them that hikers truly
experience. Something that inexperienced
hikers who only look at elevation values
alone might not anticipate or plan for.
You might plan more seriously for a
14,000 ft mountain than a 6,000 ft
mountain without realizing that the
actual vertical climb you experience on
both of them will be comparable.
There are just so many factors at play
on Mount Washington that deceive people
into underestimating its true hidden
danger only for them to end up getting
trapped unprepared, exposed to the
brutal freezing, blinding, windy weather
with nowhere to hide. All to either fall
down off of a cliff or to succumb to
hypothermia in the elements. Mount
Washington's reputation to serious
climbers is such that it's actually a
preferred training ground for the way
higher peaks up in the Himalayas like
Everest and K2 because you can
experience similar weather and climatic
conditions on Mount Washington as them
without the added threat and danger of
altitude sickness complicating things
even further. And that's great and can
be managed when you're prepared to face
it, but it's not at all for when you're
not. And there are many, many examples
from history of the more than 160
recorded deaths that have taken place on
it since 1848.
There's an entire Wikipedia list that is
specifically dedicated to all of these
victims if you'd like to go down the
rabbit hole into their individual
stories later.
And while you're probably not planning a
dangerous hike up Mount Washington, even
your usage of the internet right now in
the safety of your own home can still be
dangerous. And a great way to add a
layer of security to whatever it is you
do on the internet is by using a trusted
VPN. Like this video sponsor, NordVPN.
With NordVPN's no longs policy, your
internet service provider isn't able to
see whatever it is you're searching. And
neither does NordVPN, which actually
gives you a true incognito viewing
experience on the internet that Google's
incognito mode doesn't truly provide. I
especially like to use Nord whenever I'm
using unfamiliar Wi-Fi networks at
airports or cafes. And Nord is much more
than just a VPN. I've known creator
friends here on YouTube who've gotten
their accounts hacked after a successful
fishing attempt or a password leak. And
you've maybe even seen one or two of
them every so often whenever a normal
channel you love suddenly becomes a
crypto hype machine seemingly out of
nowhere. This unfortunately happens way
too often. And NordVPN's threat
protection includes specific features
that warn you about fishing links along
with features like a blocker for
malicious ads and dark web monitoring to
alert you if any of your passwords have
been leaked. And of course, NordVPN also
does great VPN things, too. With Nord,
you can safely browse the internet
anonymously, and your location always
stays private. It enables me to set my
location anywhere in the world and
access all the different versions of my
favorite websites. And it's the fastest
working VPN on the planet that provides
247 customer support to help you
whenever you need it, along with a
30-day money back guarantee for all
users. So, if you'd like to give NordVPN
a try, scan the QR code here on your
screen right now or click the link down
below in the description. Every purchase
of the 2-year plan will receive four
bonus months on top, and it's completely
risk-free with Nord's 30-day money back
guarantee. So, click or scan to get
started with NordVPN today. And as
always, thank you so much for watching.